Inventory of the Dangerfield Lewis Papers 1799-1854
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Dangerfield Lewis Papers, 1799-1854.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 L58
1,173 items.
This group of 1,171 items and two bound volumes, dated 1799-1854, consists chiefly of letters and accounts of Dangerfield Lewis and family of King George County, Virginia.
Dangerfield Lewis,; George Lewis,; John A. Lomax,; John Tayloe Lomax.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased: 1,173 items, 1930.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dangerfield Lewis and his father George Lewis were residents of King George County, Virginia. George Lewis was the son of Fielding Lewis and Betty Washington, the sister of George Washington.
Scope and Content Information
Letters, accounts, and legal papers of Dangerfield Lewis of "Marmion" and "Chatterton," King George County, Northern Neck, Virginia. His correspondence concerns plantation management. The collection includes account books, 1821-1829 as well as agreements with overseers, bonds for the hiring of slaves and papers concerning runaway slaves. Also includes accounts, 1816-1846, of his father George Lewis, son of Col. Fielding Lewis and Betty Washington (sister of George Washington). There is a letter [1801 ?] of a slave to John A. Lomax and other correspondence of the John Tayloe Lomax family of "Menokin", Richmond County, Virginia. Correspondents include William F. Grymes, John Taliaferro, and Henry T. Washington.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection has been organized into 3 series: 1. Letters, 2. Accounts, 3. Papers. Series 1. Letters, has been divided into the following subseries: 1. Dated Letters, 2. Fragmentary and Undated Letters. Series 2. Accounts, has been divided into the following subseries: 1. Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, 2. Accounts of Various Persons.
Arrangement
Each series are arranged chronologically by date.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Persons:
Lewis, George, d. 1821.; Lomax, John A.; Lomax, John Tayloe, 1781-1862.
Subjects:
Fugitive slaves-- Virginia.; Slavery--Virginia--History--19th century.; 1799-1854.
Geographical Names:
Marmion (King George County, Va.); Chatterton (King George County, Va.); Menokin (Richmond County, Va.)
Occupations:
Agriculture--Southern States--History--19th century.; Lawyers--Virginia--History.
Contents List
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1799-1852, n.d., 69 items. (Folder 1-2)
  - Dated Letters, 1799-1852., 60 items. (Folder 1-2)
    - William Bronaugh to [?], 1799. (Folder 1)
    - William Patton, at Ross County, Paint Creek, North Western Territory, to Major George Lewis, King George County, Virginia, 21 Nov 1800. (Folder 1)
    - [?] to John A. Lomax, at Menokin, Richmond County, Virginia, 30 June 1801 [?]. (Folder 1)
      Probably a black slave driver.
    - John Tayloe Lomax, at Menokin, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, 2 Dec 1810. (Folder 1)
    - John Tayloe Lomax, at Menokin, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, 23 Dec 1810. (Folder 1)
    - John Tayloe Lomax, at Menokin, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George [Court House], 3 June 1811. (Folder 1)
    - John Tayloe Lomax, at Menokin, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Chatterton, near King George Court House, 29 Nov 1812. (Folder 1)
    - John Tayloe Lomax, at Menokin, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Chatterton, 3 Jan 1813. (Folder 1)
    - John Tayloe Lomax, at Menokin, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George [Court House], 29 Nov 1815. (Folder 1)
    - W.W. Lewis, at Bagatelle, near Russellville, Logan County, Kentucky, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, Virginia, 15 March 1816. (Folder 1)
    - John Tayloe Lomax, at Menokin, to [?], 1 July 1816. (Folder 1)
    - D[angerfield] L[ewis] to [?], 19 Nov 1817. (Folder 1)
    - George Johnson, at King George Court House, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Oak Spring, March 1818. (Folder 1)
    - A[?] A. Smith to John Minor, 31 May 1818. (Folder 1)
    - G.F. Thornton to Mrs. Dangerfield Lewis, 3 Sept 1818. (Folder 1)
    - Robert Thomas, Jr., Madison County, to Dangerfield Lewis, King George County, 8 Sept 1820. (Folder 1)
    - S. Lewis, at Clifton Hill, [Kentucky] to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George County, Virginia, 20 June 1822. (Folder 1)
      Postmarked Morganfield, Kentucky.
    - J. Fergusson, at Westham Cottage, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Fredericksburg, 17 Aug 1822. (Folder 1)
    - J. Fergusson to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George County, 15 Oct 1822. (Folder 1)
    - A[?] A. Smith to D[angerfield] Lewis, at Marmion, 26 Nov 1822. (Folder 1)
    - Edmund G. Edrington, at Baltimore, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, near King George Court House, Virginia, 19 July 1823. (Folder 1)
    - J. Fergusson, at Richmond, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George [County], 8 Oct 1823. (Folder 1)
    - J. Fergusson, at Westham Cottage, to Dangerfield Lewis, King George County, 27 Dec 1823. (Folder 1)
    - J. Fergusson, at Westham Cottage, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George Court House, 28 Feb 1824. (Folder 1)
    - J. Fergusson, at Westham Cottage, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George County, 5 May 1824. (Folder 1)
    - Edmund G. Edrington, at Baltimore, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, near King George Court House, Virginia, 6 Aug 1824. (Folder 1)
    - George Hamilton, at Forest Hill, [near Fredericksburg] to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George County, 23 Nov 1824. (Folder 1)
    - Peter Catlett, at Morganfield, [Kentucky] to Dangerfield Lewis, King George County, Virgina, 18 May 1825. (Folder 1)
      Receipt signed by James Townsend on back of sheet.
    - G.B. Wallace to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, 21 Nov 1826. (Folder 1)
    - John Hooe, at Mt. Pleasant, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, 26 Nov 1826. (Folder 1)
    - Ann P.[?] Minor to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, 2 Dec 1826. (Folder 1)
    - E. Smith to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, 7 Jan 1827. (Folder 1)
    - Thomas H. Botts, at Fredericksburg, to D[angerfield] Lewis, at Marmion, King George Court House, 9 Aug 1827. (Folder 1)
    - William A. Knox to W. Rollow, at Marlborough, 28 Aug 1827. (Folder 1)
    - Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George [County], to Lewis W. Dangerfield, 15 Oct 1828. (Folder 1)
    - George Hamilton, at Forest Hill, near Fredericksburg, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George County, 5 Aug 1829. (Folder 1)
    - James Williams, at Fredericksburg, to Dangerfield Lewis, 27 Sept 1829. (Folder 1)
    - P.W, Thornton to D[angerfield] Lewis, at Marmion, 2 Oct 1829. (Folder 1)
    - Henry T. Washington, at Chatterton, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, 22 Feb 1830. (Folder 2)
    - [Dangerfield Lewis], at Marmion, to [Henry T. Washington, at Chatterton], 28 Feb 1830. (Folder 2)
    - D[angerfield] Lewis, at Marmion, to [Henry T. Washington, at Chatterton], 1 March 1830. (Folder 2)
    - William F. Grymes, at Brooklyn Navy Yard, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, Virginia, 10 Nov 1830. (Folder 2)
    - William F. Grymes, at Brooklyn Navy Yard, to [Dangerfield] Lewis, at King George Court House, Virginia, 26 Nov 1830. (Folder 2)
    - William F. Grymes, at Brooklyn, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, Virginia, 21 Dec 1830. (Folder 2)
    - William F. Grymes, at Brooklyn, New York, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, Virginia, 1 Feb 1831. (Folder 2)
    - John Taliaferro, at Washington, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, Virginia, 3 Feb 1831. (Folder 2)
    - William F. Grymes, at Brooklyn, New York, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, Virginia, 14 March 1831. (Folder 2)
    - William Prentiss, at Washington City, to Benjamin Johnson, at King George Court House, Virginia, 21 Feb 1832. (Folder 2)
      Including account: Dangerfield Lewis to William Prentiss, Cr.
    - [?], at Warrenton, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, Virginia, 17 Oct 1833. (Folder 2)
    - Thomas Horn[?], at Warrenton, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Court House, 26 Nov 1833. (Folder 2)
    - William Buehler, at Bedford, to John Smawley or David Barrick, St. Clairsville Hotel, 2nd Tavern, 10 Aug 1834. (Folder 2)
    - C.C. Stuart, at Chantilly P.0., Fairfax County, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Hampstead P.0., King George County, Virginia, 30 June 1839. (Folder 2)
    - George W. Lewis, at Alexandria, to his father, Dangerfield Lewis, King George County, Virginia, 23 Oct 1840. (Folder 2)
      Written on the back of a statement of progress of George W. Lewis in Alexandria Boarding School.
    - William F. McLean, at Alexandria, D.C., to [Dangerfield] Lewis, at King George [Court House], Virginia, 27 Aug 1843. (Folder 2)
      Enclosure: Business card of William McLean, grocer and commission merchant, at Alexandria, D.C.
    - G.W. Lewis to his uncle, Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, 9 Sept 1843. (Folder 2)
    - Benjamin Weaver, Jr., at Alexandria, to Dangerfield Lewis, King George County, Virginia, 23 May 1844. (Folder 2)
    - Elisha Peny, at Baltimore, to Lucinda Elington, at Fredericksburg, Virginia, 14 Oct 1844. (Folder 2)
    - [?] Miller, at Washington City, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, King George County, Virginia, 26 Nov 1845. (Folder 2)
    - John Casey, at Caseyville, Union County, Kentucky, to Dangerfield Lewis, at King George Courthouse, Virginia, 6 Feb 1846. (Folder 2)
    - Green Suttle & Co., at Alexandria, to Dangerfield Lewis, 27 Sept 1852. (Folder 2)
  - Fragmentary and Undated Letters, n.d., 9 items. (Folder 2)
    - James Ewell to [?], n.d. (Folder 2)
      Printed circular, advertising the Medical Companion.
    - J. F[ergusson] to [Dangerfield Lewis], at [Marmion], King George County, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Anna Fitzhugh to George Lewis, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - John A. Lapsley to [?] Sears, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - D[angerfield] L[ewis] to [?], n.d. (Folder 2)
    - [George W. Lewis] to his son, Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Ann P[?] Minor to Mrs. L. Lewis, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - [?] William J. Washington to Dangerfield Lewis, at Society Hill, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Henry T. Washington, at Chatterton, to Dangerfield Lewis, at Marmion, n.d. (Folder 2)
  Series 2: Accounts
- Accounts, 1807-1854, n.d. (Folder 3-10)
  - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, 1807-1854, n.d. (Folder 3-7)
    - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, debtor, 1807-1829., 306 items. (Folder 3)
    - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, debtor, 1826-1828., 1 bound volume. (Folder 3A)
      Note: This volume includes a list of live stock of Dangerfield Lewis.
    - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, debtor, 1821-1829., 1 bound volume. (Folder 3B)
      Note: This volume includes three unidentified plats of land.
    - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, debtor, 1830-1832., 61 items. (Folder 4)
    - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, debtor, 1833-1854., 189 items. (Folder 5)
    - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, debtor, n.d., 36 items. (Folder 6)
    - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, creditor, 1818-1844., 98 items. (Folder 7)
    - Accounts of Dangerfield Lewis, creditor, n.d., 12 items. (Folder 7)
  - Accounts of Various Persons, 1815-1854, n.d. (Folder 8-10)
    - Accounts of Miss [?] Lewis, 1835-1848., 9 items. (Folder 8)
    - Accounts of Miss A. Lewis, 1843., 6 items. (Folder 8)
    - Accounts of Mrs. D. Lewis, 1829-1832., 5 items. (Folder 8)
    - Accounts of Fielding Lewis, 1829-1843., 14 items. (Folder 8)
    - Accounts of Henry B. Lewis, 1846., 1 item. (Folder 8)
    - Accounts of Major George Lewis, 1819-1846., 15 items. (Folder 8)
    - Accounts of Thomas M. Lewis, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 8)
    - Accounts of various persons, 1818-1844., 127 items. (Folder 9)
    - Accounts of various persons, n.d., 10 items. (Folder 9)
    - Unidentified accounts, 1815-1854., 37 items. (Folder 10)
    - Unidentified accounts, n.d., 33 items. (Folder 10)
  Series 3: Papers
- Papers belonging to Dangerfield Lewis, 1819-1831, n.d. (Folder 11-14)
  - Copy of the will of George Lewis, 1819., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Court order appointing Dangerfield Lewis executor of George Lewis, King George County, 1823., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Note to Dan Call requesting his legal opinion as to the equity of Dangerfield Lewis in the estate of his father, George Lewis, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Memorandum concerning Revolutionary claim of George Lewis, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Certificate of sale for taxes and receipt for taxes paid on 12,000 acres of land in Logan County, Kentucky belonging to George Lewis, 1803., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Data concerning the sale of Marmion and Deep Bottom, n.d., 4 items. (Folder 11)
  - Agreement for sale of 40 acres of land in King George County by Dangerfield Lewis to David R. Jones, 1815., 2 items. (Folder 11)
  - Plats of land. Unidentified, n.d., 2 items. (Folder 11)
  - Statement by Mary Fowkes granting Dangerfield Lewis right of way through her property, 1830., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Copy of a court order appointing Dangerfield Lewis precinct road surveyor, n.d., 1 item. Copy. Mutilated. (Folder 11)
  - Agreement of Dangerfield Lewis with overseer, Nathan Burchell, n.d., 1 item. Mutilated. (Folder 11)
  - Agreement of Dangerfield Lewis with overseer, John Hicks, 1822., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Agreement of Dangerfield Lewis with overseer, Sigismund Massey, 1837., 1 item. Mutilated. (Folder 11)
  - Agreement of Dangerfield Lewis with overseer, James Bruce, 1823., 3 items. (Folder 11)
  - Dangerfield Lewis to Wily Roy Mason & C.M. Braxton, commissioners under a decree in the case of Washington's guardian vs. Braxton, 1843., 1 item. (Folder 11)
    Bond for the hire of a slave.
  - Fielding Lewis to Wily Roy Mason, 1842., 1 item. (Folder 11)
    Bond for the hire of two slaves.
  - Papers concerning a runaway slave belonging to Dangerfield Lewis, 1818., 2 items. (Folder 11)
  - Statement concerning a merino ram presented to Dangerfield Lewis, 1814., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Certificate of special bail entered by Dangerfield Lewis and Robert Sanford for Fielding Holliday in a suit brought by John Campbell in Allegany County, Maryland, 1825., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Inventory of stock, negroes and implements on the Cottage Farm, 1818., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Papers concerning an application of Dangerfield Lewis for the establishment of a public landing on the Potomac River on the Chatterton estate belonging to Henry T. Washington, 1830., 4 items. [1 piece mutilated]. (Folder 11)
  - Day book of Dangerfield Lewis, 1818-1825., 1 item. (Folder 11)
  - Fitzhugh (?) estate, n.d., 1 item. Mutilated. (Folder 12)
  - Fitzhugh (Frances) estate, 1832., 1 item. (Folder 12)
  - Fitzhugh (Lucy) estate, 1821-1832., 4 items. (Folder 12)
  - Grymes (Benjamin) estate, 1828-1831., 2 items. (Folder 12)
  - Grymes (Margaret V.) estate, 1831., 1 item. (Folder 12)
  - A copy of a subscription for Mrs. Nancy Minor, to pay her transportation to Kentucky, 1827., 1 item. (Folder 12)
  - A paper concerning the arrest in Westmoreland County of two runaway slaves. The owner's name is not given, 1811. (Folder 12)
  - A newspaper clipping concerning John Stewart, a runaway slave belonging to Henry Geat, of Virginia, 1821. (Folder 12)
  - Memoranda giving addresses of various persons, n.d., 4 items. (Folder 12)
  - Memo contains data on certain books, n.d., 1 item. Mutilated. (Folder 12)
  - Verse, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 12)
  - Printed checks of the Farmers' Bank of Virginia, at Fredericksburg, n.d., 2 items. (Folder 12)
  - Unidentified pieces and fragments, n.d., 6 items. (Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to Geo. Washington and the Washington family, n.d., 14 items. (Folder 13)
  - Pamphlet concerning the constitution of the Washington National Monument Society, Washington, 1847., 1 item. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clipping concerning the destruction by fire of "Bewdley," the old Ball homestead, in Lancaster County, Virginia, and a pen and ink sketch of the Ball coat of arms, n.d., 2 items. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clipping concerning the Bradford family including a cut of the Bradford coat of arms, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning the death of J.D. Bradford, a nephew of Jefferson Davis, 2 items. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clipping concerning the Carroll family, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clipping concerning the Carter family of Virginia, n.d. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clipping about John Randolph Tucker's eulogy upon Jefferson Davis, delivered at Lexington, Virginia, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clipping concerning the death and career of Col. George H. Elliot, U.S.A., n.d., 1 item. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clipping concerning the career of General Forest, C.S.A., n.d., 1 item. (Folder 13)
  - Obituary notices of various members of the Lewis family, n.d., 4 items. Newspaper clippings. (Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning King George County, Virginia, including sketches of Marmion, Walsingham, Canning, Millban, Belle Grove, Cleveland, Clave, Powhatan and Chatterton, n.d., 7 items. (Folder 13)
  - Other clippings, n.d., 15 items. (Folder 13)
  - Business card of Oscar Hallwig, artist, of Baltimore, who copied the original Copley portraits of Betty and Fielding Lewis, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 13)
  - Two photographic negatives of a table of Colonial design, n.d., 2 items. Photographic negatives. (Folder 13)
  - Covers from old newspapers, n.d., 16 items. (Folder 14)
  - Other covers and labels, n.d., 13 items. (Folder 14)